Don't do incremental work.
>> This is Barbara Liskov. She's a Turing
Award winner famous for her fundamental
contributions to programming languages
and distributed systems.
>> Encapsulation is a crucial part of
making modularity work. Your team is
really only as strong as your weakest
programmer.
>> I asked her for stories from her career.
That paper was the go-to statements
considered harmful. Is Dijkstra in
person also like his writing?
>> He was not always as tactful as he might
be.
>> There were people saying, "Why did she
get the Turing Award?" Why do you think
that they said that about your work?
Here's the full episode.
You applied to multiple places and
Princeton was one of them and they had
rejected you on the grounds of you being
a a woman. How did you get into
programming in an environment that's so
hostile?
>> Okay, so this was when I got my
bachelor's degree.
And I applied to several graduate
programs
in math, which is what I majored in as
an undergraduate.
And
I got this little card back. It was a
postcard from Princeton saying, "We do
not admit women."
Which was surprising.
Um I knew they didn't have women in
their undergraduate program, but I
hadn't realized it extended to the
graduate program.
Um
but you know, it was how it was. So so
what happened was I did get into
Berkeley, which is where I did my
undergraduate work. But I decided I
really wasn't ready to do a a PhD in
math and that I should get a job instead
and just sort of see you know, see how
things were.
And uh the best job offer I got was as a
programmer.
So that's how I got computer science by
a happy accident.
>> You were consistently, at least at
Berkeley, you were consistently a top
student. So, it's it it is odd that you
wouldn't even get an opportunity to play
in some cases.
>> But, that's how it was back then. It was
just I hadn't realized it was more than
an undergraduate thing. And Berkeley was
co-ed. So, you know, there
what I found was there weren't very many
women in my classes. There were lots of
women students,
but very few of them majoring in math.
And there were only maybe a couple of
women in my classes.
But,
the uh the idea that a door was shut and
women couldn't do things, that was not
what went on at Berkeley.
So, it was a different environment. Of
course, nowadays in the top schools, the
um women are about 50% in computer
science.
>> I want to talk about some of the the
core problems that you were solving in
your career. And so, I understand that
there's the software crisis in the
1970s. And uh I was wondering if you
could give the context behind what the
problem was at that time.
>> Well, it was a huge problem at the time
because
uh people did not know how to build big
programs that worked.
And so, you would often pick up the
newspaper and see an article about some
company
that had spent
uh
you know,
millions of
dollars and hundreds of man-years
developing some software system for
their company. And then in the end
they'd have to throw it away because
they it simply didn't work.
The problem was
that to get a big program that works,
you need modularity.
And you need to break your program up
into small pieces.
Each piece provides an interface with a
hopefully complete description of what
service it provides for you.
And then inside is an implementation
that's hidden and nobody pays any
attention to it on the outside.
And if you have a system organized like
that, you can actually reason about its
correctness one module at a time.
But in those days, people didn't know
how
um
they couldn't figure out how to design
systems that were modular.
And the only kind of modularity
mechanism present in programming
languages was a procedure.
And procedures didn't match the kinds of
modules you needed. Because if you think
about a file system or a database or you
know, Amazon or whatever, you know, they
they aren't a procedure where you put
something in and get something out.
They're a much more complicated thing.
So, there was no notion of a module that
sort of matched the kind of things that
people were looking for.
>> So, when you saw that problem, you know,
what were the early solutions like?
>> Well, so people were proposing
modularity and they were talking about
how important modularity was.
They didn't exactly know what a module
was.
And so, it wasn't like they could give
you a rule, this is a module. It was
just a chunk of code. In fact, there
were papers written that talked about
how big a module should be or and stuff
like that, just a chunk of code. That's
not going to work because you need
to design these systems. So, you need a
way of thinking of a design that sort of
fits into this notion of modularity.
They also didn't really know what the
rules should be for modularity.
And um
it turned out that in some of the early
work I did after grad school when I was
working at Mitre,
um I had already invented a notion of
modularity that was sort of more
complete than what people had been
talking about just because I had a small
team of programmers. We were building a
complicated system
and I wanted to keep us out of trouble.
And so I had that sort of sitting there
when I started to work on this topic.
Um,
and it enabled me to see this idea of
data abstraction
all of a sudden. I sort of saw that this
thing I had, this kind of modularity
mechanism, which consisted of basically
what I just described,
a a a bunch of code providing you with
an access through a number of what I
called operations. So you could call it
in various ways and then inside was all
hidden and whatever data it was using
was not accessible to the outside.
And then at some point I saw I could see
this as a data abstraction. It could be
a set, it could be a sequence, it could
be, you know, and so forth. And um,
and that meant we had a new type of
module.
Now when I look back at the papers from
the time, I see that idea is almost
there except people hadn't managed to
pick it out.
And so it was probably I think this
happens in science a lot. There's sort
of a time when an idea is ready and I
happened to see it.
>> You pieced these together and you put it
into the Clue programming language that
you're working on.
How did you see it influencing the
industry?
>> The first thing that happened was I
wrote a paper with um,
a a a
a man who was a graduate student at MIT,
Steve Zilles, about this idea of data
abstraction and it sketched a notion of
what abstract data types would be and
how a programming language could support
them. And this was a very um,
is a very impactful paper.
And so there was a a big impact on the
research community.
And then
Clu came along and that involved a lot
of additional research in the in the
programming language area.
The next thing that happened, so people
were watching this in the research
community, but of course people who are
in companies that want to write
programs,
they need a programming language.
And
I decided I wasn't going to try and turn
Clu into a
product because that would have required
working in a company. In those days you
didn't just put software out on the
internet and people used it. There
wasn't an internet yet for one thing.
And and I was much more interested in
doing research than in
you know, working in a company. So I put
Clu on the side. It had a user base.
But I it but for companies to use a
programming language in those days, they
wanted a company behind that language.
The next thing that happened was the
government uh put out a call for uh a
programming language they could use.
This led to the Ada programming
language.
That um
so you know, that was already a big
impact if you think about it. That there
there was a language explicitly being uh
designed to have data abstraction in it.
And then
finally in the '90s Java came along.
>> I thought it'd be interesting cuz you
you worked on Clu. You designed that
programming language to ask you about
other programming languages. You said
somewhere that there's something wrong
with Python and I was curious to hear
your thoughts of why.
>> Python
has modules, but it doesn't have
encapsulation. So it allows code on the
outside to muck around with what's going
on on the inside of a module. And that's
all I was talking about. Encapsulation
is a is a crucial part of making
modularity work.
And when you're building big programs,
so you have many programmers working on
them,
your team is really only as strong as
your weakest programmer.
So, it's nice if the compiler can
enforce things and make certain kinds of
bad behavior not possible. I mean,
Python is you know, has another intended
use. It's helping naive programmers
learn quickly how to write programs and
stuff like that.
And people in the programming language
world do think about issues like this.
Like, you know, how to make
languages safer and so forth. But, since
I stopped working in that area, I'm no
longer an expert in programming
languages.
>> What got you into distributed computing?
>> I read a paper by Bob Kahn, who was with
then Cerf considered to be, you know,
the founders of the internet.
And Bob talked about
um
his dream of distributed computing,
where you would have a program composed
of pieces on different computers
connected by a network.
And nobody knew how to build those
programs. And so, I just thought, great
problem.
>> [laughter]
>> And [snorts] I was looking for a new
problem, so I jumped into distributed
computing.
And the first project was actually a
programming language to write
distributed programs in.
And and then I started looking at other
problems in the distributed systems
area.
>> What was that first programming language
that
>> It was called Argus. It was It was very
strongly influenced by Clu.
It was an object-oriented language.
Had a special kind of object called a
guardian,
which was a module sitting at a single
computer.
And then guardians could compute
communicate through remote procedure
calls.
One of the things you run into in
distributed computing
um is if you have a computation that
starts at one guardian and then makes
use of other guardians at other nodes in
the network, in the end, you want that
computation to either complete entirely
or have no effect at all.
And how do you do that? Well, I borrowed
the notion of transactions coming out of
the database field.
And that was part of how Argus worked.
It ran computations as atomic
transactions.
>> Oh, interesting. Like distributed
transactions across those nodes.
>> And I think it led right into the work I
did on um viewstamp replication, which
was
um that was the beginning of cloud
storage. I was thinking in terms of a
file system, but it doesn't really
matter what it is. You know, how do you
have data out on the internet stored at
multiple sites
with correct behavior
and always accessible as long as enough
nodes are up and running and the network
is working.
>> I see. And what is viewstamp in this
context?
>> Oh, that had to do with some details of
how the system worked. And it was a way
of noticing when some nodes failed and
other nodes had to take over, you could
figure out which ones had the most
recent state in them, so you could pick
up and not lose anything that had not
had that had happened in the past.
>> Uh what what if the clocks are out of
sync? Like
>> Uh it had nothing to do with clocks
because it was just numbers.
In other words, we were in view 25, the
next view was 26. So
>> Oh, okay. Just incrementing some numbers
that are passed around.
>> This reminds me a lot of uh Leslie
Lamport's work.
>> Actually, yes.
>> Did you ever work with him or
>> No. Leslie and I developed what is
essentially the same idea independently.
And he had the system he called Paxos
and I had this thing called view stamp
replication.
>> Oh, interesting. And they're essentially
the same thing.
>> They are. Yeah.
>> Oh, are there pros and cons of the two
approaches?
>> Yeah, I mean that when you do this kind
of system, there's a lots of little
details you can play around with. So,
you could, you know, decide to do it it
gets technical, but you know, there's
tiny differences. But no, they're
basically the same. In fact, what
happened was
uh the first time that
I was aware of that this was actually
used in a real system was when the
Google file system came along.
And
one of my former students who was a I
think he was a consultant at Google
looked at what was going on in there and
he said, "Oh, he says that's view stamp
replication." So, the people at Google
seemed to think it was Paxos, but in
fact, they are the same system.
>> I also noticed like um when you were
uh when you came up with abstract data
types
maybe I mean maybe it's just cuz there
wasn't the internet wasn't as, you know,
wasn't there that there was also the
object-oriented stuff going on on the
West Coast.
>> Yes, Alan Kay was developing Smalltalk
at the same time that I was working on
Clu, and then at Carnegie Mellon uh Bill
Wulf and Mary Shaw were working on
Alphard, which was another data
abstraction language.
And you're right, there was no there was
no internet, although there was the
ARPANET.
You know, so we did but it was like
there were two independent streams of
research going on and we weren't talking
to each other.
And so, I wasn't paying much attention
to Smalltalk and
on the West Coast, I don't think they
were paying much attention to data
abstraction.
And this led to the Liskov substitution
principle
which I mean, the story is a sort of a
cute one because
in 1986, I think it was, I was asked to
give a keynote at OOPSLA.
OOPSLA is the object-oriented
programming conference, and this was the
second year it was happening.
And so, I decided I think I'll read all
those papers about Smalltalk, and there
were other languages being developed
that were based on Smalltalk, and see
what's going on with them. And I
discovered
Um so, Smalltalk has this idea of
inheritance in it, where you can have a
class and a subclass which borrows from
the way the class is implemented and
changes it a bit.
And Clu doesn't have that. Clu just has
what we call clusters, and they're all
independent.
So, I saw that they were talking about
this notion of classes and subclasses.
And
and then I saw that they were also
talking about something they called type
hierarchy.
Where they wanted the type implemented
by a class
to be related in some way that they
didn't understand to the type that was
implemented by a subclass.
I really thought about modules in terms
of their specifications.
This partly had to do with a class I
developed at MIT
that I developed jointly with my
colleague John Guttag.
And in that class, we taught the
students how to do design, about
modularity, data types, and so forth,
but also how to write specifications,
how to reason about correctness.
And so, it had a big focus on think
about the meaning of things first, and
the implementation is something that's
kind of hidden inside, and you don't
worry about it very much. And so,
that was a different way of thinking
about things than what was going on in
the
on the West Coast, where they were
really thinking in terms of
classes and subclasses. And I even saw
papers where they would describe the
behavior of a class by explaining how
its implementation was different from
the implementation of the superclass.
So, they were kind of focused on
implementations in a way that we
weren't. And so,
when I read these papers about type
hierarchy and I saw they just couldn't
figure out what it was supposed to mean,
I was thinking about it from the terms
of meaning. And so, I was able to say it
has to do with the behavior.
And this subclass better behave like the
superclass if you use it in an
environment where the superclass is
expected.
And that became what ended up being
called the Liskov substitution
principle.
And ultimately, Jeannette Wing and I
wrote a paper on behavioral subtyping,
which is the formal definition.
>> And then, how did it get that name? Cuz
you didn't go off on stage and say, "Hey
everyone, here's the Liskov substitution
principle."
>> one day in the
in the '90s, after the internet had
arrived, I got an email saying, "Can you
say if this is the correct
interpretation of the Liskov
substitution principle?" That's when I
discovered
that
>> [laughter]
>> there was such a name.
And And I
I don't think I had really been aware of
how important it was until that point,
because I wasn't thinking about this
stuff. I was working on other stuff.
>> In the academic community, it seems very
reasonable to have multiple people have
similar ideas. But it seems like some
ideas stick
more than others. For instance, like the
Viewstamped Replication versus Paxos.
They're the same thing. I'm wondering,
like, in that case for instance, why
would Paxos be more known than
Viewstamped Replication?
>> Yeah. So, what Leslie says is,
"I went around giving all the talks, and
she implemented it."
>> [laughter]
>> Really?
>> Something up to that.
>> Then he
got notoriety for speaking about it.
>> Yeah, he he he did give lots of talks
about it and wrote several papers and so
forth and I didn't realize it was the
same system. But finally it became clear
that they were the same system.
>> I also wonder how much the name matters
because Paxos is kind of catchy, you
know.
>> It is a cute name.
>> It's a cute name, yeah.
>> Yeah, right.
>> So, I I could see maybe it has better
marketing around the idea, I guess.
>> I also think that
this approach to solving this problem,
which both Leslie and I picked up
independently, in my case came from the
work I'd been doing with transactions.
Because in transactions there's a leader
that
you know, says now we're going to commit
and ask everybody can we commit and if
they all say okay, you know, it's
but unlike in transactions
of in transactions if the leader fails,
there's what's called, you know, the
this can be a real problem. Here we had
to have a way of moving to a new leader
if the old leader failed and that's the
big step forward that happened in both
Viewstamped Replication and and Paxos.
Now, there was also Byzantine fault
tolerance, which came along later that
was developed. So,
Viewstamped Replication I developed with
my student Brian Oki. It was his PhD
thesis.
And then Paxos I developed with my
student Miguel Castro. It was his PhD
student thesis.
And
Miguel got interested in this problem
because
uh there was a DARPA request for
proposals
and there was one about this problem on
the internet. By then there were
Byzantine attacks and you know,
malicious attacks and
nodes that would
purport to be working correctly, but
actually they had been compromised and
so forth and so
Viewstamped application in Paxos only
handled crashes and um
if there were messages that were had
been played with, you could tell when
they arrived that they were bad. And
that was about the extent of what we
dealt with.
But these malicious attacks with nodes
that purported to be working when they
weren't, that was a big step forward.
And Miguel saw this request for
proposals and he said to me, "Why don't
we see whether we can come up with a
protocol that works in the presence of
Byzantine attacks?" And
and I think by the way, Leslie is the
one that invented the word Byzantine to
>> I think he did.
>> Yeah, right.
>> I saw in the in the software crisis
stuff. There's the paper with Dijkstra
that you had mentioned was one of the
papers you you wrote that said, "We need
modularity." And that paper was the
go-to statements considered harmful.
>> Right.
>> And I'm curious cuz Dijkstra, I mean,
when I was studying computer science,
you we all know his name. Did you ever
meet him or work with him?
>> Oh, yeah, many ti- I did never worked
with him, but I did meet him multiple
times. And uh you know, he had very
interesting ideas. And that
paper, uh go-to statement considered
harmful, it's not actually a paper. It
was a letter to the editor of the
Communications of the ACM.
But it was very impactful. And
what was really important about that
paper was that Dijkstra was talking
about
how difficult it is to reason about the
correctness of code.
And this was at a time when
in the sciences,
computer science was kind of dismissed
as nothing much.
And anybody can write code.
And you know, Dijkstra was trying to
make a point, which I think was actually
important, that it it's not as trivial
as you think it is. It's not trivial at
all.
Um and he was also pointing out that
go-tos can be misused.
>> And it was controversial at the time.
>> It was, yeah.
>> But today I I I don't I mean I've
written code for yeah, over a decade.
>> People don't use go-tos.
>> have I have I haven't even seen a go-to
in the code.
So, what why was it controversial at the
time?
>> The programming languages were different
then.
Um first of all, there were people
writing programs in assembler.
In assembler, you have to use go-tos.
Programming languages didn't have
some of the constructs in them that we
think of today.
And uh so some people were using go-tos
cuz they had to.
And also
um compilers didn't do all the kinds of
optimizations that they do today. So,
there was a concern if you didn't have
go-tos, maybe your program wouldn't be
efficient enough.
And then
uh there were people who used go-tos and
wrote really good code, and they weren't
offended that Dijkstra was saying your
code is bad.
So, there was a whole but and and
Dijkstra was not the most um diplomatic
person. So,
>> [laughter]
>> you know, so he he didn't write it in
the you know, nice
not you can imagine writing that paper
more nicely where you said um
So, it that but there were many reasons
why it was controversial. You know,
people were offended, but then there
were also concerns about
like programming languages don't have
these features I need, what am I
supposed to do?
And then there were concerns about what
the compiler was doing. And so, the
world is very different now. But
clearly, Dijkstra won the day.
>> Yeah, he did.
>> Because
no go-tos.
>> [laughter]
>> And is Dijkstra in person
also like his writing?
>> Uh he was not always as tactful as he
might be.
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah, but you know, he was a a very uh,
distinguished researcher.
>> Computer science has had such a huge
impact on the industry.
Why did you choose to stay in academia
instead of going into industry?
>> So,
I like doing research.
And I enjoy working with students.
And
I teaching was never my favorite thing,
but I always felt teaching and research
were very closely connected.
Um, but also it was a different time.
So,
this business about how professors are
all forming companies and so forth,
which goes on today, that wasn't
happening 20 years ago.
Or maybe it was happening 20 years ago,
but 30 years ago it wasn't. So, when I
was young, it wasn't the thing that you
did. It was sort of a
either or sort of thing. So, I wasn't
even thinking about doing stuff like
that.
I did work in a startup briefly at the
end of the '90s. I didn't like it.
I much prefer doing research and as a
professor you have this it's it's a gift
and a curse.
The gift is you can do whatever you
want. The curse is you have to figure
out what it is that you're doing.
But I like that freedom. And the fact
that I just could go off in any I mean,
my career is full of these interesting
zigzags where I would switch to
something else. I had the freedom to do
that.
>> What stops you from going off in a very
useless direction?
>> Uh, you won't get tenure.
>> [laughter]
>> Who's the judge?
>> The community.
Yeah, it's not you know, what what the
way that you're viewed at your
university
has mostly to do with um,
one a very important facet of it is how
are you viewed in your research
community.
So,
because that's one of the important
things they want
from their faculty if you're in a
research university.
>> You mentioned earlier that
research and teaching were heavily
related in your opinion.
Why is that?
>> Because when you teach, you have to
teach from first principles.
And if you're doing good research, you
need to understand deeply
what's working, what's not working, what
assumptions you're making. It's It's
really the same thought process.
>> It's It sounds like in research
I mean, and this is true in every walk
of life. There's the I guess the
direction that you take
and then the work that you do towards
that direction. And it sounds like for
research the
the direction is
maybe the most important thing cuz you
could have a phenomenal researcher
doing an idea that
has no you know, even if you did it at
100% it's not going to lead to anything.
>> So, you you know, I you tell students
graduate students don't do incremental
work.
Don't you know, you've got you you can't
just keep working on the same thing over
and over just making little teeny
improvements. You need to find You're
right, you have to find a good problem,
but you also have to find a problem
that's amenable to a solution and one
that matches your skill set.
And
you have to recognize when you're going
in a good direction versus not going in
a good direction.
>> Looking back on your career, you say
that it was luck and that it seems like
things just
fit together.
>> I feel there was luck involved.
There was a lot of hard work involved.
There was
um not allowing
uh something negative to
you know, cause you great difficulty.
So, for example, when I
finished my PhD, I would have liked a
faculty position.
But, I didn't have any good offers.
So, I went back to Mitre, the company I
had worked for initially as a
researcher.
Um in other words, I just kept on
marching along and it turned out to be a
very good choice because I was switching
from AI to systems and this gave me I
worked there for 4 years. Gave me 4
years to make that transition without
having to uh worry about students and
teaching and all the other stuff, you
know, so it worked out well.
But, it also meant that I didn't, you
know, feel really sorry for myself that
I didn't get a job. It meant I just kept
on going.
And then, Title IX was about to be
passed and finally
academia was opening up to women and I
was ready.
But, I think, you know, when I talk to
other people about their careers, they
talk about doors opening and doors
closing. So,
um
I didn't get the academic job I wanted,
but I had this other opportunity. I
majored in math and fortunately, I was
offered a programming job. I mean,
doors opened and then you have to
decide, am I going to step through? And
this is a pattern that people see in
their careers. It's not just me, many
people have
have those kinds of choices that you
make along the way, opportunities and
things that aren't so great, you know,
and you're sort of working your way
through.
>> I've interviewed a few people who have
won Turing Awards and I've done research
and
watched a lot of these speeches that
people give after they receive the award
and I noticed something
different in in your speech or some of
the stuff that I read about uh your work
which is that in yours it seems like
when you got the Turing Award
there were people saying
why did she get the Turing Award? It was
kind of negative commentary on that.
And I didn't see that in the other
cases. Why do you think that they said
that about your work?
>> So, I'm I'm not so sure this doesn't
happen to other people by the way. It
was just that my husband was out on the
internet By the way, there was an
internet by then.
>> Okay.
>> Okay. [laughter]
As you know, the internet is not
necessarily nice.
>> I know that.
>> Right.
And um
so
I I can imagine that other people might
have had the similar a similar
experience had they bothered to look.
Um
but I also think that
the world had changed so much and
the work that I had done was so basic to
what was going on
that people really didn't understand
that there was a before.
I mean, my graduate students really
didn't understand that there was a
before because I discovered that at the
time I got the award. It really hadn't
struck them that data abstraction didn't
always exist.
So, I think that
I mean, I viewed it as
a in a way a huge compliment
not really just to me, but to the group
of researchers who you know, all
together got us to the point where we
had uh these modular programming
languages and we understood about
abstract data types and we understood
about how to reason about correctness.
All that stuff was so fundamental
that people thought there was no time
when it hadn't already existed.
>> So, they took it for granted.
>> They took it for granted. I mean, the
Byzantine fault tolerance, you look at
that, there's a protocol.
And
you can understand that there was a
protocol, somebody invented that
protocol.
Um you know, so you get the credit for
that. This was much more fundamental.
This was the whole mindset you had about
how to develop programs. And that's what
people were talking about.
And things had changed so much
that all these inventions of mine and
others were just there in the woodwork
and people didn't realize that there was
a time before.
>> That's validating then. That it's it's
so impactful and
everyone uses all the time that they
don't even know what it was like before
what you did.
>> So, I thought, you know, it's a huge The
person who said it didn't mean it
nicely, but I thought
really it's a huge a huge compliment.
And and a statement about where we are
now as opposed to where we were then.
So,
>> Okay, well, that's all the questions I
have for you. Thank you so much for for
your time. Really appreciate it.
>> You're welcome.
>> Thank you for listening to the podcast.
It's a passion project of mine that I've
really enjoyed building. Another passion
project that I've been working on kind
of in secret is building an ergonomic
keyboard that I wish existed and I
finally have a prototype, so I'd love to
show you what we've built. It's
ultra-low profile and ergonomic and I
couldn't find anything like it on the
market, so that's why we built it. I'll
put a link to the keyboard in the
description. You can take a look and
learn more about the project there. We
could definitely use your support. Also,
if you have any feedback for me about
the show, I'd love to hear it. Comments
on YouTube have led to guests coming on
like Ilya Grigorik and David Fowler. I
wasn't aware of them until someone
dropped a comment. Also, feedback in the
comments helped me learn to reduce the
number of cliffhangers in the intros.
So, your comments definitely make a
difference. Please keep letting me know
what you'd like to see more of in the
show, and I'll see you in the next
episode.